Time's up.
But, sir, I'm not finished yet.
Miss King, you've had all the time
allowed.
Gentlemen, please hand in your completed
reports.
Sir, it really isn't fair.
They're in Paris and I'm working alone.
Naturally, it would take me longer.
I really don't want to hear your
complaints, Miss King.
You can't keep up the work. You don't
belong in university.
The fact is, young lady, women don't
belong in medical school.
This is as much work to be in pre -med
as any man.
When it comes to women, they are so
prejudiced. I'm glad I like women.
Listen, I've got an idea. Let's go to
the Citadel or the Prince of Wales
I can't. I've got errands to do.
I only have one more day in Halifax, and
all I've done is help you move so far.
Do you think it's fun moving boxes with
books up all those stairs?
Fine. Go home, then.
I've got so much work to do.
It's only the first week, and I'm
already behind.
I did everything for you. I moved that
sofa for you, and I lugged that desk
from the store, didn't I?
Hey, Felicity!
Don't be such a grump. Hold on.
Over there.
No,
no,
no. Don't! Here.
Oh, I'm sorry.
There he is.
The guy.
Over here, guy.
I should be dreadfully annoyed with you,
guest pipe, for keeping me waiting like
this. What are you hiding behind your
back?
Well, you're right.
What are you wrong? Aren't we going to
say hello?
Close.
It's delicious.
I guess we're not going to say hello.
I'm going to whip you up the most
scrumptious strawberry tart you ever did
taste.
I'll take that.
Here,
dear.
practically threw herself at him.
Right there in public.
It was the most outrageous display of
bad manners.
She was really pretty.
Pretty?
Felix, you've got no taste whatsoever.
Gus seemed to like her.
Who cares what Gus Pike likes?
Right. Who cares what Gus Pike likes?
Hope he marries her.
Yeah, I hope he marries her, too.
Who Gus marries is no concern of mine.
Ah, me neither.
He went away to sea, you went to medical
school.
End of story.
Felix, don't look at me like that.
Mary and Gus was the furthest thing from
my mind.
So I wish you would just stop talking
about him.
Me?
All I wanted to do was say hello.
Felicity, what did you expect?
Did you really think he was going to
wait for you to make up your mind
But he gave me his ruby ring.
That was ages ago.
Promise you won't get angry if I ask you
a question.
Don't be ridiculous.
Did you write and tell him you loved him
and you'd marry him?
Why would I do such a thing?
Women don't propose to men.
Let me rephrase that.
Did he write and say he loved you and
he'd marry you?
No.
Not exactly.
What's the problem?
You don't love each other. Why couldn't
I just say hello?
Felix, when you see him again, say
hello.
Say hello all day and all night. Do I
care?
It means nothing to me.
Nothing whatsoever.
In that case, I have one more question.
If you don't care for him, why are you
still wearing his ring?
There. There.
I'm not wearing it. Satisfied?
And not only am I not going to wear it,
I'm going to throw it in his face and
tell him that he has not been a
gentleman.
Why? What did he do wrong? I don't get
it.
Of course you don't.
You're a boy.
Boys don't get anything.
Excuse me.
I'm looking for a sailor named Gus.
Gus Pike.
Pike.
Pike, you say?
He's young.
He's got dark hair. A place of fiddle.
That's him.
You wouldn't happen to know where he
lived.
Well, maybe I do, and maybe I don't.
Well, I guess to my age, never can tell
what he remembers.
Let's see.
Well, then perhaps this will refresh
your memory.
A quarter?
Let me see now.
Pike.
What's that pike with a P?
Well, of course it's with a P.
There. That's all the change I've got.
Over at Captain Ames' house, Crisco
Street.
That's where young guests stay these
days.
Thank you.
Why do I have to go in with you? This is
going to be very embarrassing.
Because if we go in together, it's just
a visit.
If I go in by myself, it'll look
suspicious, like I came just to see him.
But you did.
Yes, may I help you?
Hello.
I'm Felicity King, and this is my
brother Felix.
We just happened to be passing in the...
In the neighborhood.
Felicity.
Felix.
Hello, Gus.
Oh, for heaven's sake, you're the famous
King. Gus has told me all about you.
I'm Charlotte Ames.
Do come in. We were just about to have
tea.
So where do you... See, Felicity?
Please. I do hope you like oolong.
Gus brought it back for me.
Oh, how thoughtful of him.
Could have knocked me over with a
feather seeing you two out the door like
He never wrote until school started.
I'd find him in the first place.
Oh, we just went down to the... What's
that you were saying, Felix?
He wasn't saying anything.
Milk? Please.
Sugar? Thank you.
So Gus told me all about Avonlea. Oh, it
sounds like a darling little place.
Do try the strawberry tarts, Felicity.
Oh, no thank you. I'm afraid I break out
in welts from strawberries.
So does Felix.
What a shame.
Gus loves strawberries, don't you?
So tell me, Felicity.
I'm fascinated.
You are going to medical school. How
daring.
Are you enjoying it?
Enjoying it? You should have seen her
yesterday.
Felix.
Well, I certainly admire your courage.
All those difficult subjects, science
and such. I'm afraid my poor little
just couldn't absorb it.
Like a man's could.
Good grief, are you all right?
Fine.
Couldn't be better.
Do try some of these.
Now, you and your brother don't break
out into wealth over butter cookies, do
you now? We love butter cookies.
I'm sorry, but we don't want to outstay
our welcome.
Felix has to catch the ferry back to
Avonlea.
Oh, but you just got here.
And you haven't met a very important
member of the Ames family, hmm?
No? And what do you think?
Just a moment. I'll be right back.
What was that all about?
Yeah, what'd I do?
Not another word out of you, Felix King.
And as for you, Gus Pike, I only came to
give you this.
Felicity!
Why'd you give me the ring back?
I don't want it.
You can give it to Charlotte.
Charlotte? Well, you don't expect me to
wear it, do you? Of course I do. I gave
it to you.
I'm not accustomed to wearing jewelry
that comes with a curse.
A curse? What curse?
You.
The next thing you got.
Gus, is anything wrong?
I don't know.
But it left.
Oh, darling, I'm afraid I rushed you for
nothing. I wanted you to meet Gus's
friends from Avonlea. Felicity King and
her brother.
Oh, what a shame.
Felicity.
Wasn't that the name of the girl you
were forever mooning about while we were
sea, Gus?
Oh, you shouldn't have let her run off
without introducing me.
Never mind.
I'll make it up to you.
Wait till you try the strawberry tart.
Come along, Gus.
father my love and don't breathe a word
about anything why not because i
Hate them an old maid, tails them not.
I've been looking everywhere for you. We
gotta talk.
I told you I've got nothing to say to
you.
Felicity, don't be like that.
Felicity King, I don't know what
happened at the Ames place today, and I
know what's going on here, but you had
no call giving me back this ring.
I gave it to you, and it belongs to you.
Take it.
Why?
Won't Charlotte wear it?
Now, don't start that again.
Why would Charlotte Ames wear this ring?
Well, why wouldn't she?
You are engaged to her, aren't you?
Engaged?
Where'd she get a ridiculous notion like
that?
Charlotte Ames is married to the captain
of the ship I was on.
She's married?
Well, you could have written and told me
instead of letting me make a fool of
myself.
How could I write about something that
didn't happen?
Dear Felicity, guess what?
I'm not engaged to Charlotte Ames.
Besides, I don't recall you saying much
of anything in your letters.
Well, I was waiting for you to say
something.
Why should I be the first one to say
something? Now, hold on, Felicity.
I don't have time to argue with you, Gus
Pike.
I've got more important things to do.
Gus, I'm sorry.
Same here.
Heck, we're not babies anymore,
Felicity. We can't keep squabbling like
Can we go somewhere and talk?
Sure glad we had a chance to talk,
Felicity, but I should probably get you
now.
Sweet roses.
Two blooms for a penny.
What's that you say?
It's the flower lady.
Roses.
Red roses.
Roses red as blood.
How much for the whole bunch?
Huh?
Ezekiel.
What?
Ezekiel Crane.
Captain Crane, you came back.
They lied.
All of them.
Lies!
What's that?
What about Captain Crane?
Ruby Red.
The captain said, wait,
wait for the roses to bloom.
Ruby Red.
No, wait!
Come on.
Wait!
Mom!
I need... I need quick... Ruby Red died
from the night. I need...
We're not going to hurt you. What is he
talking about?
I don't know, but something got her
spooked.
He called me Captain Crane.
How do you know him?
I won't give you no trouble.
I swear I won't.
Just don't.
Don't let them take me.
Leave her be.
But she recognized the ring. She knew it
was Captain Crane's.
She looked me right in the eye like she
knew me.
You're him.
Ezekiel Crane.
Really, men can't see past their noses.
It's very simple.
Captain Crane lived a sailor's life. He
stopped in a thousand ports, met a
thousand women.
We have no right to bother this poor
woman.
Let's just leave her alone.
Here?
In a place like this?
What else can we do?
This is where she lives.
Besides, we don't even know her name.
She'll cut your death in a night like
that.
It's going to pour for sure.
Let's take her back to your place.
My place?
I can't do that.
Take her to the angels.
I can't. I'm just staying there until I
find a room of my own.
Besides, they'd never understand.
I see. They won't understand.
But I'm supposed to take a perfect
stranger back to my room.
If she's a friend of Captain Crane,
she's no stranger.
I got this feeling, Felicity.
Something tells me we're doing wrong if
we leave her here.
I've never seen neither of them ever
again!
Are you asleep yet?
Yes.
I'm not.
Well, thank you for telling me.
Sorry.
Night.
Felicity?
What?
She's sleeping like a baby.
Everybody in Halifax is sleeping like a
baby, Gus.
Except for you and I.
Look, I'm sorry I can't stay up all
night and talk. I've just got such a
day ahead of me tomorrow.
I think it's best if we just think of
night.
Night.
Gus?
Gee, Felicity.
How's a fella supposed to sleep if you
keep pestering him?
Why are you going to so much trouble for
someone you just bumped into?
Most of my life, kind of like a big
empty hole,
never knowing who I am or where I come
from.
You're Felicity King. You're from
Avonlea.
You know your mother and father, your
whole family.
Me, I don't know nothing but myself,
except a few things I can't
forget, like my mother's gravestone.
Eliza Pike, born 1863, died 1894.
Then there's Abe Pike, the pa.
He's nothing to brag about.
What is it?
Do you think there's something that this
woman might know?
I'm not sure.
She's gnawing away at me, though,
thinking about things.
Maybe I should stop dragging up what's
best for God.
And I say to myself, no, keep digging,
get to the bottom of it.
Difficult to put the path to where it
belongs.
Look at you and me.
Do we belong to the past?
You're a part of me, Felicity.
I don't have no past.
Meeting you and your family was when my
life started.
What can I do, Gus?
Do you want me to help you?
I'm not pushing you anymore, Felicity.
I'm just asking you to stick with me a
while longer.
Until I figure out what's going on here.
It's like... When you smell the sea and
you hear the wind howling.
The sky's still clear.
What you know on your bones, a storm's
brewing.
It's like that.
We're on to something, you and me.
Don't ask me why.
I just know it.
There.
You're looking all prettied up.
Would you like some more tea?
It was a present from Captain Crane.
Gave it to me before he left.
Sail the seven seas, Captain.
I won't know.
I won't tell.
Look, I know what you think, but I'm not
Ezekiel Crane.
The ring with his, you got that part
right.
But I'm not him.
How do you do?
My name's Gus Pike.
I'm only trying to make friends.
No.
No, they took him away.
He's lost. He's lost.
Who's lost?
Friends say, how do you do?
My name's Gus Pike.
What's yours?
She's like the swallow that flies so
high
Like the river that never runs dry
She's like the sun...
Am I crazy thinking what I'm thinking?
There could be a million Elizas.
It's a very common name.
That's true. I know it's true.
But my mother's name was Eliza. Gosh,
she can't be your mother. You told me
your mother died years ago.
Besides, we don't even know her last
name, and she's not about to tell us.
She's the right age, Felicity.
And her eyes...
Help my butter eyes.
Can't be.
Can it?
You know it's impossible.
You came across someone with the same
name as your mother.
Call it fate, but that's all it is.
I don't think so.
That's not all it is.
Gus, you're letting your imagination run
away with you.
Let's use common sense.
Let's go to the police and turn her over
for safekeeping.
The police?
No.
I can't do that.
All right, not the police.
But there are places for people like
her, Gus.
Nice places.
I've read about them.
We'll find one.
look at you.
She can't stay here. She's been here
before.
You know her? She tries to run.
We can't have that sort. It upsets the
others.
What do you mean she tries to run? Did
she escape from here?
Oh, plenty of times.
What's her last name?
They don't have last names. Not real
ones.
They get put here.
You mean somebody brought her here?
Who?
You must keep records of such things. We
don't keep records.
They pay their money, we don't ask
questions.
Now, come on now.
I wouldn't leave a dog in a place like
this.
If there's a chance back in Avonlea,
even a small one, I need to know.
Gus, it's such a wild idea.
I hope you'll stick with me for
yesterday.
You know I will.
Daniel King, if you don't stop eating
those, you're going to have a very sore
tummy tonight.
Janet, make sure you core those
properly.
Yes, Henry.
Daniel, you leave those apples alone. I
didn't get them just for you. Daniel.
Oh, Felicity.
Oh, Gus.
Gus Pike, is this really you?
It's great to see you, Miss King.
Felicity. Why are you home from school?
What's wrong? Are you sick? Mother,
mother, please don't get excited. I'll
explain everything later.
Sorry to bother you like this, Miss
King, but I have something important I
to talk to you about.
You and Felicity.
Felicity, what is wrong? I demand to
know why you're at home from school
now.
Mother, Aunt Hedy, we brought someone
with us.
This is Eliza.
I don't believe I caught your last name.
She hasn't got one, Mrs. King.
Felicity, dear, give me a hand with
these dishes, will you?
Excuse me.
Felicity, dear, before I make an article
of myself, who is this person?
Daddy, it's going to be difficult to
understand.
Gus. I'm not disturbing you, am I?
I've made us some hot chocolate.
Good. I'm glad you're still up.
Got a lot on my mind.
It took me a while to quiet her down.
Dear me.
It looks like you got yourself in a fine
mess this time.
You think I did wrong bringing Eliza
here?
Well, I... Oh, no.
No, dear boy.
Heaven is where your home is.
Home is where you go when you're in
trouble.
You do seem to attract trouble in
inordinately large doses.
I hope you're not doubting me, Miss
Kang.
I have never doubted you, Gaspite.
Not from the minute I first met you.
Though I swear I've never met a soul
more determined than you are.
That's what Felicity says.
It is still Felicity, then.
Always was.
I'll tell you this, Miss King.
She's there for me when I'm in a jam.
Love's something more than merely
pulling one another out of jams, you
What's she to do if... if school refuses
to take her back?
I don't know.
And I'm worried about that.
I want her dreams to come true, Miss
King, and I don't want to wreck them for
her.
Perhaps you are her dream, Gaspik.
I wish I was.
I wish a whole lot of things.
Miss King, about Eliza.
Do you think I'm chasing a ghost or
what?
Far as we know, your mother is dead,
boy.
Terrible as that is. Surely you must try
to put all that behind you and get on
with your life.
I can't.
I can't get past it no matter how hard I
try.
Did you ever hear talk from anyone?
About my mother, I mean.
It's of course about us both.
It was ages ago.
Can you remember what it was? I need to
know.
Let me see.
Oh, yes.
Some hearsay of Rachel Lynn's, if I
recall.
Something about Abe Pike's wife, your
mother, coming from a farm.
Out past Pat Fruin's place. Pat Fruin,
you say?
I've been here before.
I don't know when.
She remembers something.
Do you want to go up there?
No.
There's another way.
It's no use.
No, no.
You've
done
all you could.
No, I didn't.
What?
There's still a grave.
Oh, God, no.
I have to see if she's buried there.
You can't do it.
That's all I got left, Felicity.
Please hurry up. If anyone finds us
here, we're going to be... Come on,
Felicity, don't be so scared.
Felix King, I'm not afraid.
Well, Gus, it's your mother.
You open it up.
Nothing but a pile of mud.
And think of desecrating a grave as a
serious crime.
I realize this is important to you, but
in my opinion, you have to abandon this
search. You understand?
But the coffin was empty.
Doesn't that prove anything?
That doesn't mean that that woman in the
kitchen is your mother.
But it's possible, isn't it?
It's true, Mother.
Maybe it wasn't before.
But you have to admit that now there is
a possibility.
Isn't there, Felix?
Oh, yeah, sure.
Anything else you want to dig up, Gus?
She knows this ring.
She knows Captain Crane.
I don't care if it sounds crazy. I'm
looking after her. Please don't do this
yourself.
What you want to be real just isn't.
She's nobody, Gus.
She's just a vagrant you found on a city
street.
Oh, you persist in this, you'll wind up
wandering around with her for the rest
of your life.
Faith up to the truth, Gus Pike.
That woman will be nothing but a burden
to you.
I can't imagine what it was like for you
as a child.
upstairs. Daniel, where did she go?
He doesn't know.
I'll take the woods.
I'll look around the house.
Felix, come with me.
Eliza?
Eliza!
The devil's pulpit!
It ain't a plank.
It's true.
Everything I thought...
Captain Crane.
To Eliza.
My own true love.
You've got to tell me.
Why was this buried under the devil's
pulpit?
I can't go on knowing only bits and
pieces.
You married Abe.
with the Captain Crane you loved.
Captain Crane.
Isn't he my pa?
What about Abe Pike?
Did he know?
You've got to remember what happened.
Did Abe Pike bury the coffin and tell
everyone you were dead?
Was it Abe putting you in asylum?
He
wrecked
your life.
And mine too.
There's my boy.
There's my little boy.
What do you want me to do?
I'll do anything you want.
I have to take Eliza and find Captain
Crane, even if he's in Jamaica.
If anyone knows the truth about us, he
does.
We're off.
Goodbye.
Yes, it is.
Soon you'll marry me, Felicity.
Don't let me go without a promise this
time.
Say you'll be mine.
I've always been yours, Gus.
I'll be yours forever.